Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis records
1976-1981
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis
1.1 linear feet
The scattered records of the Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis date from 1976 to 1981 and measure 1.1 linear feet. Founded in 1975, the organization offered a venue for avant-garde and experimental film as well as special merit documentaries. The records consist of scattered business and administrative records, including member information, the constitution, and by-laws; one folder of correspondence; various notes; printed materials; and a large number of files on filmmakers.
Provenance
Amy Halpern, one of the founders of the Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis donated the records in 1994.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Historical Note
The Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis was founded by a group of independent filmmakers, critics, and theorists in March 1976. The mission of the non-profit organization was to provide a southern California venue for mostly experimental and avant-garde film.
The Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis operated as a member group, and in addition to showing film, offered the opportunity for new and established filmmakers to interact and exchange ideas, and to promote cinematography as a fine art. The Oasis held film screenings about twice monthly in the gallery of the Los Angeles Institute for Contemporary Art. Although most of the films were experimental or avant-garde, the members also showed some feature films and documentaries considered to be particularly important. The Oasis served as the only regular screening venue in Los Angeles at which new and unknown filmmakers could show their works. The Oasis was dissolved in 1981.
Members and founders of the Oasis included Paul Arthur, Roberta Friedman, Leslie Gehry, Lynn Gerry, Amy Halpern, Tom Lesser, Sandy Matthews, Beverly O'Neill, Pat O'Neill, Magdalena Rangel, Tim Shepard, Grahame Weinbren, Susan Rosenblum, Brent Wilcox, Diana Wilson, David Wilson and Arlene Zeichner.
The Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis showed films by Kenneth Anger, Bruce Baillie, John Baldessari, Stan Brakhage, Rudy Burckhardt, Bruce Conner, John Cornell, Maya Deren, Jules Engel, Morgan Fisher, Oskar Fischinger, Hollis Frampton, Robert Huot, Larry Jordan, Fernand Leger, William Moritz, Susan Pitt, Hans Richter, Michael Snow, Chick Strand, John Whitney, and Emerson Woelffer, among others.
Scope and Content Note
The scattered records of the Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis date from 1976 to 1981 and measure 1.1 linear feet. The records consist of scattered business and administrative records, one folder of correspondence, various notes, printed materials, and a large number of files on filmmakers and cinematographers.
Scattered business and administrative records include the constitution and by-laws of the organization, founding information, contracts, member information, film rental documents, and film screening schedules. Resumes are found for Oasis members Morgan Fisher, Roberta Friedman, Leslie Gehry, Lyn Gerry, Amy Halpern, Beverly and Pat O'Neill, and William Moritz.
There is one folder of scattered correspondence dating from circa 1977-1981, financial notes, meeting notes, and program notes. Printed materials include announcements and posters, printed articles written by members, clippings, press releases, and film programs.
The largest series consists of compiled files on filmmakers and cinematographers, most of whom showed at the Oasis. Files contain a variety of materials, such as clippings, reviews, programs, biographies, and notes.
Arrangement
The records are arranged into five series:
Series 1: Scattered Business Records, 1976-1981 (Box 1; 13 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1977-1981(Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 3: Notes, circa 1979-1980 (Box 1; 4 folders)
Series 4: Printed Material, circa 1976-1981 (Box 1, OV 2; 0.25 linear feet)
Series 5: Filmmakers' Files, 1976-1981 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Fisher, Morgan; Friedman, Roberta; Gehry, Leslie; Gerry, Lyn; Halpern, Amy; Möritz, William; O'Neill, Beverly; O'Neill, Pat, 1939-
Subjects-Topical:
Cinematographers; Filmmakers -- California -- Los Angeles; Experimental films
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Scattered Business Records, 1976-1981, Series 1:; (Box 1; 13 folders)
  Scattered business records include contracts, grant proposals, film rental agreements, the constitution and by-laws, a check ledger, written histories of the organization, schedules of film screenings, tax information, a job description, forms, and publicity contacts. Also found are resumes of Oasis members Morgan Fisher, Roberta Friedman, Leslie Gehry, Lyn Gerry, Amy Halpern, Beverly and Pat O'Neill, and William Moritz.
  See Index for List of Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis Screenings from Series 1.
  Index: List of Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis Screenings from Series 1
  Below is a list of all known film screenings held at the Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis as documented within the records.
  Date Film Screening
  1976 March 7 Norman Zammitt
  1976 April 8 New Westerns
  1976 April 22 Films by Women Independent Filmmakers
  1976 May 2 Landscapes: An Exploration of Open Spaces
  1976 May 16 Chick Strand
  1976 May 30 Funny Business
  1976 June 6 Werner Schroeter
  1976 June 6 Udo Serke
  1976 June 13 Eastern Influences
  1976 July 25 House Blend
  1976 August 22 Thom Anderson
  1976 August 22 David Lamelas
  1976 August 22 Robert Nelson
  1976 August 29 An Evening of Deranged Funnies
  1976 October 3 Pat O'Neill
  1976 October 17 Rudy Burckhardt
  1976 October 31 William Raban
  1976 November 21 New British Avant-Garde, Part 1
  1976 November 28 New British Avant-Garde, Part 2
  1976 December 12 L.A. Today
  1977 January 9 Trollstenen
  1977 January 23 Night Cleaners
  1977 February 6 L.A. Today
  1977 February 27 Jack Goldstein
  1977 April 10 Robert Breer
  1977 April 24 Hollis Frampton
  1977 May 8 James McBride
  1977 May 8 Kenneth Anger
  1977 May 8 George Kuchar
  1977 May 15 Robert Bresson
  1977 May 29 Films with Few Images
  1977 June 12 Michael Snow
  1977 June 26 The Naked and the Nude
  1977 July 10 Eye Music, San Francisco
  1977 July 24 Films by Jean-Marie Straub and Thom Anderson
  1977 September 18 Michael Snow
  1977 September 18 Robert Nelson
  1977 October 2 The Films of Gary Beydler
  1977 October 16 Maya Deren
  1977 October 16 Andrew Noren
  1977 October 16 Dore O
  1977 November 5 Paul Sharits
  1977 November 6 Hollis Frampton
  1977 November 6 David Wilson
  1977 November 6 Victor Grauer
  1977 November 6 Bruce Conner
  1977 November 20 Films by Women
  1977 December 4 Juvenile Liason
  1977 December 18 Rosa von Praunheim
  1978 January 15 Artifacts from the Machine Age
  1978 January 29 Kenji Mizoguchi
  1978 February 12 The Present Remembered
  1978 February 26 Films by Jean-Marie Straub
  1978 March 12 Oasis Potluck
  1978 March 19 Warren Sonbert
  1978 April 2 Dan Graham
  1978 April 16 James Broughton
  1978 April 30 Jon Jost
  1978 May 21 John Whitney
  1978 May 28 Hans Richter
  1978 June 11 Hollis Frampton
  1978 July 2 White, Scorsese, Gutman
  1978 July 16 Gottheim, Benning
  1978 July 23 Robert Nelson
  1978 July 30 Lenny Lipton
  1978 August 13 Some Interesting New Films
  1978 August 27 Super 8 Films
  1978 September 17 Kenji Mizoguchi
  1978 September 24 Bruce Conner
  1978 September 24 Bruce Baillie
  1978 September 24 Danny Lyons
  1978 October 1 Victor Faccinto
  1978 October 15 Jon Rubin
  1978 October 29 Lewis Hock
  1978 November 19 Films of Ernie Gehr and Vincent Grenier
  1978 November 26 Richard Meyers
  1978 December 3 Yvonne Rainer
  1978 December 10 Joseph Cornell
  1979 January 14 Martha Haslanger
  1979 January 28 William Moritz
  1979 February 18 Roy Barge
  1979 February 24-25 Ondine with Chelsea Girls
  1979 March 11 James Benning
  1979 April 1 Suzan Pitt
  1979 April 8 Ericka Beckman
  1979 April 22 Animation
  1979 May 27 Ernie Gehr
  1979 June 3 Babette Mangolte
  1979 June 10 Robert Bresson
  1979 June 17 Maya Deren
  1979 June 24 Andrew Noren
  1979 September 23 Stan Brakhage
  1979 September 30 Emerson Woelffer
  1979 October 7 Roberta Friedman
  1979 October 7 Grahame Weinbren
  1979 October 14 Larry Gottheim
  1979 October 28 James Whitney
  1979 November 4 Guvnor Nelson
  1979 November 4 Dorothy Wiley
  1979 November 11 George Griffin
  1979 November 18 Bill Brand
  1979 November 25 Chick Strand
  1979 December 2 Malcolm Le Grice
  1979 December 9 Suzan Pitt
  1979 December 9 Tim Shepard
  1979 December 9 Anita Thatcher
  1979 December 16 New Animated Shorts
  1980 January 1 Oskar Fischinger
  1980 January 28 Roberta Friedman
  1980 January 28 Grahame Weinbren
  1980 February 10 Danny Lyons
  1980 February 10 Chick Strand
  1980 February 10 Bruce Conner
  1980 February 17 Dennis Pies
  1980 February 24 Amos Poe
  1980 March 2 Pat's Selection
  1980 March 9 Vincent Grenier
  1980 March 16 Henry Hills
  1980 March 23 New Bay Area Films
  1980 March 30 Manuel De Landa
  1980 April 6 Robert Huot
  1980 April 13 Oblowitz, McCall, Gordon
  1980 April 20 Lionel Soukaz
  1980 April 20 Guy Hocquenhem
  1980 April 27 J.J. Murphy
  1980 May 11 Owen Land
  1980 May 18 Rick Blanchard
  1980 May 25 Yvonne Blanchard
  1980 June 1 Larry Jordan
  1980 June 15 Robert Frank
  1980 June 22 Oasis Group Show
  1980 June 29 The Italian Olfactory Cinema of Gianikian and Ricci Lucchi
  1980 September 21 Salt for Svanetia
  1980 September 28 John Baldessari
  1980 October 5 Ann Arbor Film Festival
  1980 October 12 Bruce Baillie
  1980 October 19 Birnbaum, Haslanger, Keller
  1980 October 26 Ethnographic Films
  1980 November 2 Rob Danielson
  1980 November 9 Smithson, Serra, Oldenburg, Mangolte and Childs
  1980 November 16 Jonas Mekas
  1980 November 23 Saint Carmin's Choice
  1980 December 7 Jean Pierre Gorin
  1980 December 14 Pat O'Neill
  1981 March 15 Susan Kleckner
  1981 June 21 Michael Snow
  1981 June 28 Polish Avant-Garde
  1981 July 5 Alex Cox
  1981 July 5 Amy Halpern
  1981 July 12 Chicago Filmmakers; Edited by Harvey Nosowitz
  1981 July 19 The Oasis Police Show
  1981 July 26 Stan Brakhage
  1981 August 2 Political Newsreels
  1981 August 23 Pat O'Neill
  - Check Ledger, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, circa 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Contracts, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Film Rentals, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Grant Proposals, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Historical Information, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Job Description, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Member Information, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publicity Contacts, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Schedules of Film Screenings, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tax Information, 1977, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Work Schedules, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, circa 1977-1981, Series 2:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  There is one folder of scattered correspondence.
  - General Correspondence, circa 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Notes, circa 1979-1980, Series 3:; (Box 1; 4 folders)
  This series consists of scattered notes relating to meetings, finances, and programs.
  - Notes, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Financial Notes, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Meeting Notes, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Program Notes, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Printed Material, circa 1976-1981, Series 4:; (Box 1, OV 2; 0.25 linear feet)
  This series consists of announcements, posters, printed articles by and about Oasis, clippings, newsletters from the Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art (LAICA), film programs, business cards, Oasis letterhead, and press releases.
  - Announcements and Posters, 1976-1981, (Oversized Items housed in OV2) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Articles Written by Oasis Members, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Business Cards, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - LAICA Newsletters, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Membership Forms, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Program Drafts, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Oasis Letterhead, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Press Releases, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Oasis Programs, 1976-1981, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
  - Oversized Announcements and Posters, 1976-1981, (From Box 1, F19) (Box 2 (OV))
- Filmmaker and Artists Files, 1976-1981, Series 5:; (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
  Found here are files about filmmakers, cinematographers, and other film artists that showed at the Los Angeles Independent Film Oasis. There are also a few files relating to specific film programs held at the Oasis. Files may include a variety of scattered clippings, reviews, programs, biographies and notes. See the Index for Series 1 for a list of all film screenings held by Oasis.
  - Anderson, Thom, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Ann Arbor Film Festival, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Artifacts from the Machine Age, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Baillie, Bruce, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Baldessari, John, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Beckman, Ericka, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Berry, David, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Berwick Street Film Collective of London, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Beydler, Gary, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Birnbaum, Dara, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Blanchard, Rick, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Brand, Bill, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Breer, Robert, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Bresson, Robert, 1977, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - British Avant-Garde Film, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Broomfield, Nicholas and Churchill, Joan, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Broughton, James, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Burckhardt, Rudy, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Churchill, Joan, 1977, (See Box 1, F45) (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Conner, Bruce, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Cornell, Joseph, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Danielson, Rob, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - DeLanda, Manuel, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Demetrakas, Johanna, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Deren, Maya, 1977, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - The Eastern Influence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Ethnographic Films, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Eye Music, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Faccinto, Victor,1978 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Films by Women, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Firestone, Cinda, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Fischinger, Oskar (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Frampton, Hollis, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Frank, Robert, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Friedman, Roberta (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Funny Business, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Gehr, Ernie, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Goldstein, Jack, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Gordon, Bette, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Gottheim, Larry, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Graham, Dan, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Grauer, Victor, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Haslanger, Martha, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Hock, Louis, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Hocquenghem, Guy, 1980, (See Box 1, F113) (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - House Blend, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Huot, Robert, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Iimura, Taka, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Jordan, Larry, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Jost, Jon, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Kalatazof, Mikhail, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Keller, Marjorie, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Kleckner, Susan, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Lamelas, David, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Land, Owen (formerly George Landow), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Landscapes, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Lyons, Danny, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Lipton, Lenny, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - McBride, James, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Mangotte, Babette, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Mekas, James, 1976, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Mizoguchi, Kenji, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Moritz, William, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Murphy, J.J., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - The Naked and the Nude, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Nelson, Robert, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - New Animated Shorts, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - New Westerns, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - O'Neill, Pat, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Oblowitz, Michael, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Pies, Dennis, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Pitt, Suzan, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Poe, Amos, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - The Present Remembered, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Raban, William, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Rainer, Yvonne, 1977, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Regan, Chris, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Richter, Hans, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Rosenfeld, Susan, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Schroeter, Werner, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Serke, Udo, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Sharits, Paul, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Snow, Michael, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Sonbert, Warren, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Soukas, Lionel and Hocquenghem, Guy, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Strand, Chick, 1976, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Straub, Jean-Marie, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Vigil, Carmen, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - von Praunheim, Rosa, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Whitney, John, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 119)